Guide to the Dennis Gale papers, 1903-1985 MS2191.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Dennis Gale papers
1903-1989
1966-1983
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gale, Dennis E.
MS2191.UA
4 Linear Feet
This collection includes research notes, clippings, reports, notes from interviews, dissertation drafts, correspondence, dissertations, and photographs. Most of the material dates from 1966-1983. These are the papers of Dennis Gale from his time teaching and working on his dissertation at George Washington University. This collection consists of materials on the history of Georgetown and on urban planning and development.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquisition data is unknown for this collection.
Historical or Biographical Note
Dennis Gale was a professor of Urban and Regional Planning at GWU from academic year 1976/77 to 1990/91. He completed a Ph.D. dissertation about historical restoration in Georgetown at GWU in 1981.
Dennis Gale is currently a Senior Research Fellow for Metropolitan Studies on the Newark campus of Rutgers-The State University of New Jersey. He is also Professor of Public Administration and Political Science at Rutgers. Gale has earned the following degrees: B.A., 1964 Bucknell University (English Literature); M.Sc., 1968 Boston University (Journalism); M.Ed, 1969 Harvard University (Urban Affairs); M.C.P., 1971 University of Pennsylvania (City Planning); and PhD, 1982 George Washington University (American Civilization). In the 1970s Gale was an urban planning consultant in Washington, D.C. and later served as Director of Planning and Management Research at The Urban Institute in Washington. He began his academic career in 1975 at George Washington University, where he attained the rank of Professor and served as Director of the Center for Washington Area Studies. While at George Washington University he shared the Dilthey Prize for faculty research in 1984. He was a visiting faculty member at the University of Nottingham, England, in the early 1980s. From 1995 to 2000 he was Chair of the Department of Urban and Regional Planning at Florida Atlantic University, where he was appointed the Henry D. Epstein Professor of Urban and Regional Planning.
Gale is the author of three books: Understanding Urban Unrest: From Reverend King to Rodney King (Sage Books, 1996). Washington, D.C.: Inner City Revitalization and Minority Suburbanization (Temple University Press, 1987). Neighborhood Revitalization and the Postindustrial City (Lexington Books, 1984). Additionally, he has contributed articles to seven scholarly books and has published numerous articles in refereed journals including Journal of the American Planning Association, Journal of Planning Education and Research, Journal of Planning Literature, and Urban Affairs Review.
Gale has lectured at several institutions, including American University, Bates College, Colby College, M.I.T., the Kennedy School at Harvard, the Woodrow Wilson School at Princeton, University of Reading (England), and the University of Florida. He has also lectured at the U.S. Bureau of the Census, National Trust for Historic Preservation, U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, and the American consulate in Berlin, Germany.
He has been the recipient or co-recipient of grants from the Florida Institute of Government, Florida Office of Coastal Programs, University of Southern Maine, University of Maine System, Apple Computer Co., George Washington University, U.S. Agency for International Development, U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, and German Marshall Fund.
In 1978 Gale was appointed to the White House Conference on Balanced National Growth and Economic Development by President Jimmy Carter. He has served on the boards of several civic organizations in Washington, D.C., Maine, and Florida. Currently, he is a member of the New Jersey Committee of the Regional Plan Association and co-chair of the Smart Growth Consortium at Rutgers.
He is the father of two children and lives in New Jersey.
(Source: www.cornwall.rutgers.edu/Gale.htm, 2003)
Collection Scope and Content
This collection includes research notes, newspaper and magazine clippings, reports on urban development, book summaries, notes from interviews, dissertation drafts, correspondence, dissertations, and photographs. The material dates from 1903-1989, but most of the material dates from 1966-1983. These are the papers of Dennis Gale from his time teaching and working on his dissertation at George Washington University. This collection consists of materials on the history of Georgetown and the subjects of urban planning and development. The collection contains research material (including notes from interviews and photographs) used in writing his dissertation and several drafts of the dissertation, which was titled Restoration in Georgetown 1915-1965. The collection is organized into two series: Dissertation research and Subject files.
Arrangement note
Organized into two series: Dissertation research and Subject files
Photographs; City planning -- Washington (D.C.); Georgetown (Washington, D.C.)
- Dissertation research, 1903-1985; 1966-1982; Series 1; 2.5 Linear Feet
  Arrangement note
  The Dissertation research series contains all the research notes, source material, drafts, etc. associated with Gale's dissertation on Georgetown's history and redevelopment. The Dissertation research series folders is organized in groups of like material, beginning with preliminary dissertation work and ending with the finished dissertation.
  Scope and Content note
  This series includes research notes, newspaper and magazine clippings, reports on urban development, book summaries, notes from interviews, dissertation drafts, correspondence, dissertations, and photographs. The material dates from 1903-1985, but most of the material dates from 1966-1982. These are the papers of Dennis Gale from when he was working on his Ph.D. dissertation at the George Washington University. This collection consists of materials on the history of Georgetown and the subjects of urban planning and development. The collection contains research material (including notes from interviews and photographs) used in writing his dissertation and several drafts of the dissertation, which was titled Restoration in Georgetown 1915-1965.
  - Dissertation proposal material, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Working bibliography, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Georgetown Canal and Riverside Proposal, 1962; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Georgetown Waterfront Symposium, 03/22/1965; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - A History of Grace Episcopal Church Georgetown, 1974-1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - City Scape, 10/1975; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Georgetown 1980: A Program for the Coming Decade, 1969; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Georgetown Historic Waterfront, 1968; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - National Capital Planning Commission: Georgetown Waterfront Area Plan and Development Program, 07/25/1975; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Eileen Zeitz Ph.D. dissertation and notes, 1978; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Information: Values of Residential Properties in Urban Historic Districts, Georgetown, DC, 1977; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - L'Enfants Methods and Features of his Plan for the Federal City, 1975; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Changes fo Federal Employment in the National Capital Region 1977-78, 1978; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Georgetown Market Restoration Analysis, 04/1966; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Columbia Historical Society Newsletter, 1980-1982; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Copies of articles about Georgetown redevelopment, 1961-1971; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Various articles and clippings, 1934-1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - From People and Land, 1950; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Various clippings and articles, 1909-1985; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Various clippings, 1979-1982; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper reviews, 05/22/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notes and articles, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Book summaries and notes, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Notes, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Material for second draft (notes and clippings), 1903-1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Notes, articles, and clippings, 1931-1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Notes and graphs, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Population / census, 1910-1940; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cost of living, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Employment 1916-21, 1930-40, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - From "A Study in the Resettlement of an Urban Area" and notes, 1951-1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Occupancy and mobility 1916-21, 1930-40, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Elite list, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Housing DC and Georgetown 1934, MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1960 census tracts, MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Vacancies 1916-1921, 1930-40, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Housing DC 1940-1950, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Building activity 1915-27, 1928-58, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Members of congress in Georgetown, circa 1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Copies of maps, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Note cards (from box) [1 of 2], undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Note cards (from box) [2 of 2], undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - City directory sample note cards, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Note cards Washington and Georgetown data on population, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Note cards bundle, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sources - not on DC per se - note cards, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Note cards bundle, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sources on DC note cards, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Note cards, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Note cards, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Georgetown, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Jon Reynold, 03/01/1982; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Everett Payne, 03/05/1982; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Dorothea deSchweinitz, 11/02/1978; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Armistead Peter - 1644 31st st Tudor Pl, 12/08/1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - J. Bernard Wyckoff, 11/24/1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Capt. Peter Belin, 11/25/1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - John Gill, 12/05/1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - G. Chapman, 12/04/1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Howard McPeck, 12/05/1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Howard Cayton - 3069 Canal St, 12/08/1980; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Hubbard, Gillette, Lyle, and Hinton, circa 1980s; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mary Creamer, 02/08/1981-02/24/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Statement of Rev. J.D. Foy, undated; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Visit to Mt. Zion United Methodist Church, 1980-03/07/1982; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Introduction handwritten, 1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Part I: Georgetown in the 18th and 19th centuries - handwritten draft, circa 1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Part II: Early Remodelling 1915-1922 - handwritten draft, circa 1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Part III: Roots of Preservation 1933-1945 - handwritten draft, circa 1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Part IV: The Maturation of Preservation 1946-65 - handwritten draft, circa 1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Part V: The Culture of Historic Restoration - handwritten draft, circa 1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Footnotes - handwritten draft, circa 1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence about dissertation, 1979-1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Comments on dissertation draft, 1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Letters regarding finished dissertation, 1981-1982; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - New Bloods, Bluebloods, and Just Plain Folks: The Restoration of Georgetown 1915-65, 04/16/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - New Bloods, Bluebloods, and Just Plain Folks: The Restoration of Georgetown 1915-65, 04/16/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - New Bloods, Bluebloods, and Just Plain Folks: The Restoration of Georgetown 1915-65, 04/16/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Dennis Gale final examination notice, 07/09/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Restoration in Georgetown 1915-1965 [1 of 2], 09/30/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Restoration in Georgetown 1915-1965 [2 of 2], 09/30/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Dissertation: Restoration in Georgetown, Washington, DC, 1915-1965 [1 of 2], 09/30/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Dissertation: Restoration in Georgetown, Washington, DC, 1915-1965 [2 of 2], 09/30/1981; MS2191 Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Subject files, 1963-1989; 1966-1983; Series 2; 1.5 Linear Feet
  The Subject files series is a collection of materials organized and filed by Dennis Gale on various urban development topics. The Subject files series is arranged alphabetical by folder title, as that seems to have been Gale's arrangement.
  This series includes newspaper and magazine clippings, reports on urban development, notes, correspondence, transparencies, and essays. The material dates from 1963-1989, but most of the material dates from 1966-1983. These are the papers of Dennis Gale from his time teaching at the George Washington University. This collection consists of materials about Washington, DC, Georgetown, and urban planning and development.
  - Archictural styles transparencies, undated; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - British new town data, 1979-1980; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Convention centers, 1985; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Conversion of non-residential properties to residential properties, 1975-1987; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Federal tax policy, 1968-1986; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Ft. Lincoln (new town), 1972-1980; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - History in urban planning education, 1977-1986; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Housing and community development, legislation, regulation, etc. [1 of 2], 1974-1981; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Housing and community development, legislation, regulation, etc. [2 of 2], 1975-1977; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Model cities / H.U.D. [1 of 2], 1969-1970; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Model cities / H.U.D. [2 of 2], 1968-1969; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - New communities [1 of 2], 1967-1989; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - New communities [2 of 2], 1967-1989; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Office development, 1972-1988; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Real estate econ analysis, 1981-1984; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Real estate speculation taxes, 1973-1979; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Real property tax, 1973-1982; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Recycling buildings, 1974-1984; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Rent control - national or other than DC, 1976-1986; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Shopping centers, 1985-1986; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Site value tax, 1963-1977; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Tax base sharing, 1971-1978; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - UDAG, 1985; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Urban analysis comparative - U.S., 1975-1986; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Urban quality of life [1 of 2], 1966-1979; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Urban quality of life [2 of 2], 1966-1979; MS2191 Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 9)